Guide to the Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, Videorecordings SC1209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings, 2001-2014
  - Kurtzig, Andy, Birth of a Business, 2012-03-07; 2923; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur Andy Kurtzig talks about the birth of his current venture, JustAnswer. Kurtzig developed the idea for the paid question and answer platform when his wife, who was pregnant at the time, wanted on-demand answers to medical questions.
  - Kurtzig, Andy, Company Missions Matter, 2012-03-07; 2924; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur Andy Kurtzig explains why he was wrong when it comes to the importance of company missions. Here he explains what changed his mind on this issue, and how his company utilizes its mission when attracting talent and hiring.
  - Church, Jeff, The Wave of Social Entrepreneurship [Entire Talk], 2012-04-11; 2933; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur and successful executive Church, Jeff founded Nika Water to create a thriving social enterprise that supports clean water projects in impoverished countries. In this inspiring lecture, Church lays out his motivations for striking out on his own, the challenges of the global water crisis and the essential lessons aspiring entrepreneurs need to learn.
  - Church, Jeff, Shaped by Formative Experiences, 2012-04-11; 2934; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur Church, Jeff describes some of the formative, early-life experiences that would go on to encourage later interest in becoming an entrepreneur and social enterprise advocate.
  - Church, Jeff, Take the Shot, 2012-04-11; 2935; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Nika Water Co-Founder Church, Jeff encourages individuals to fully embrace opportunity when it shows up at the door. To avoid regret later in life, people must take the shot to do something extraordinary, says Church.
  - Church, Jeff, Sharing Upside, Avoiding Dilution, 2012-04-11; 2936; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Experienced executive Church, Jeff warns young entrepreneurs to avoid unnecessary dilution when bringing team members in on new ventures. According to Church, there are ways to share upside without giving away too much.
  - Church, Jeff, Can Products Save the World?, 2012-04-11; 2937; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur Church, Jeff discusses whether social enterprises can sell products to affect change in the world. As the co-founder of social enterprise Nika Water, Church believes social entrepreneurs can only have lasting success if they start their enterprises as "nine parts business, one part cause."
  - Church, Jeff, Social Entrepreneurship is Growing, 2012-04-11; 2938; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Nika Water Co-Founder Church, Jeff shares the factors causing the coming wave of social entrepreneurship, including young people, the Internet, celebrities and baby boomers.
  - Church, Jeff, Why Nika Water was Started, 2012-04-11; 2939; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Social entrepreneur Church, Jeff tells the story of Nika Water's inception, which came about after his family's experiences working on water projects during a trip to Africa.
  - Church, Jeff, Conscious Consumerism, 2012-04-11; 2940; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Experienced executive and social entrepreneur Church, Jeff details four forces behind the growing interest in "conscious consumerism" and shares customer behavior data around cause-based products.
  - Church, Jeff, Lessons for Venture Starters, 2012-04-11; 2941; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Experienced executive Church, Jeff offers some lessons to keep in mind when launching commercial and social entrepreneurial ventures: 1) Don't quit early; 2) Find partners that balance you; and 3) Remember the rule of 2's.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Producing a Career from the Ground Up [Entire Talk], 2012-04-18; 2942; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Acclaimed film and television producer Gale Anne Hurd knows what it takes to build a career from scratch in a tough industry. Hurd describes her path from entry-level roles in the entertainment industry to becoming a leader in the Hollywood community, based on taking chances, making yourself indispensable and staying committed to what you love.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Ready for the Big Question?, 2012-04-18; 2943; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    No matter what industry you choose to enter, are you ready to answer the big question: What do you ultimately want to do in this business? Acclaimed film and television producer Gale Anne Hurd relates being surprised by this question during her first interview with legendary filmmaker Roger Corman.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Pulling Through Challenging Roles, 2012-04-18; 2944; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Gale Anne Hurd discusses the challenges of taking on an important role early in her film career. Working as the one-person marketing department for legendary filmmaker Roger Corman, Hurd made many personal sacrifices while gaining valuable experience that led to her next opportunity.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Learn More by Starting at the Bottom, 2012-04-18; 2945; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Acclaimed film and television producer Gale Anne Hurd tells the story of leaving a role in marketing to take an entry-level position on a film set. It was hard to watch peers in other industries succeeding during this period, says Hurd, but she values the decision she made to accept the challenge of starting over, making herself indispensible on set and earning the respect of her colleagues.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Partners and Mentors Play a Role in Success, 2012-04-18; 2946; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Film and television producer Gale Anne Hurd shares how partners and mentors played a critical role in the making of her first film, The Terminator, with director Jim Cameron. Hurd also offers some secrets to building a successful career.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Opportunities in Content Creation, 2012-04-18; 2947; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Producer Gale Anne Hurd explains why the entertainment industry is ripe with opportunity for creators of content. She also describes why Hollywood is now looking online to find fresh talent leveraging new, lower-cost technologies to tell their stories.
  - Hurd, Gale Anne, Content Piracy, 2012-04-18; 2948; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Film and television producer Gale Anne Hurd offers a candid and direct response to an audience question regarding her feelings around online piracy and the illegal distribution of content.
  - Hwang, Rebeca, Small Acts and Big Impacts [Entire Talk], 2012-05-02; 2949; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    This special lecture offers insights from two leaders creating impact through entrepreneurship. Founder Samara-Rubio, Elizabeth explains how her company, StorWatts, aims to provide distributed energy storage to millions around the world, while YouNoodle entrepreneur Rebeca Hwang tells stories of her early field experiences which formed her passion for social entrepreneurship.
  - Samara-Rubio, Elizabeth, A Perspective for Life, 2012-05-02; 2950; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    StorWatts Founder and CEO Samara-Rubio, Elizabeth shares an experience from childhood that forever altered her understanding of what it means to work with limited resources.
  - Hwang, Rebeca, Social Entrepreneurs and Self-Actualization, 2012-05-02; 2951; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Based on Maslow's Hierarchy of Needs, entrepreneur Rebeca Hwang shares why she believes social entrepreneurs are aiming to achieve self-actualization by helping others gain basic happiness through meeting their basic survival needs.
  - Hwang, Rebeca, You Don't Know Everything, 2012-05-02; 2952; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneur Rebeca Hwang talks about her experiences at MIT, where she built products in the lab and then deployed them in the field to solve real world problems. Hwang also discusses why technologists don't know everything, and why spending time in the field is necessary to appreciate all the institutional factors in play.
  - Hwang, Rebeca, Making Good Decisions, 2012-05-02; 2953; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneurs Samara-Rubio, Elizabeth and Rebeca Hwang each describe their considerations when making decisions. For Samara-Rubio this means knowing what you want and acting with purpose; for Hwang, it's about either narrowing or enlarging your number of possible opportunities.
  - Hwang, Rebeca, How Do You Assess Talent?, 2012-05-02; 2954; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Samara-Rubio, Elizabeth and Rebeca Hwang, the founders of StorWatts and YouNoodle, respectively, share what they look for when assessing talent or prospective business partners. Having the ability to recover from adversity and possessing actual operating experience are particularly appealing characteristics to Samara-Rubio, while Hwang seeks partners with a value system that aligns with her own, and who possess complementary skill sets and a healthy obsession.
  - Murray, Brian, Changes in the Publishing Industry, 2012-05-09; 2955; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    HarperCollins CEO and President Murray, Brian describes how the publishing industry landscape has fundamentally changed since he arrived at the company in the late 1990s.
  - Murray, Brian, When You Launch 12 Products a Day, 2012-05-09; 2956; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    HarperColliins CEO and President Murray, Brian shares some interesting statistics from his company's operations. As the world's third-largest English language publisher, the company must re-invent its revenue streams each year, says Murray, and contend with supplying content to new platforms while launching, on average, 12 new products per day.
  - Murray, Brian, Content Creators as the Brand, 2012-05-09; 2957; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Murray, Brian, CEO and president of HarperCollins, the publishing industry has traditionally functioned using a business-to-business model, eschewing direct relationships with consumers. In conversation with STVP Executive Director Seelig, Tina, Murray explains why his company puts its authors forward as the brand.
  - Murray, Brian, Publishers Act as Venture Capitalists, 2012-05-09; 2958; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Murray, Brian explains why publishing companies function much like venture capitalists, investing millions of dollars a year into developing new products in a culture business. Here the CEO and president of HarperCollins also articulates how the company leverages their understanding of the marketplace when placing bets on authors and projects.
  - Murray, Brian, Finding the Right Digital Ecosystem, 2012-05-09; 2959; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    HarperCollins CEO and President Murray, Brian talks about challenges and opportunities he sees on the horizon in the publishing industry. One of the primary issues, says Murray, is ensuring that the right digital ecosystem exists to continue to produce, market and sell books.
  - Murray, Brian, On Digital Rights Management, 2012-05-09; 2960; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    The issue of using digital rights management (DRM) technologies on content is a complicated one, says HarperCollins CEO and President Murray, Brian. Here he shares both the benefits and disadvantages of DRM, and describes tests being conducted to find a solution balancing a company's intellectual property rights with consumer desire to transfer files.
  - Murray, Brian, Partners as "Frenemies", 2012-05-09; 2961; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    As a powerful distribution channel and a growing competitor in publishing, Amazon plays a disruptive role in the publishing industry. HarperCollins CEO and President Murray, Brian describes the "complicated relationship" publishers have with Amazon, who is a partner they work with and compete against. "The term 'frenemy' is a great term to capture what business is like today," says Murray, here in conversation with STVP Executive Director Seelig, Tina.
  - Murray, Brian, What Engineers Bring to the CEO Role, 2012-05-09; 2962; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    In response to a question from STVP Executive Director Seelig, Tina, HarperCollins CEO Murray, Brian explains how his early engineering background continues to serve him as leader of a major publishing company. Murray believes engineers are solvers of complicated problems by training, and that, "a publishing company, any company, is one big, complex problem" needing to be solved.
  - Murray, Brian, A Story of Change and Opportunity [Entire Talk], 2012-05-09; 2963; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    HarperCollins President and CEO Murray, Brian discusses the shifting economics of publishing and how his company, which launches 12 new products per day, is working to succeed in this disruptive period. In conversation with STVP Executive Director Dr. Seelig, Tina, Murray also talks about issues of digital rights management, his company's willingness to explore new business models, and how HarperCollins manages relationships with other major players in the space.
  - Ek, Daniel, A Playlist for Entrepreneurs [Entire Talk], 2012-05-16; 2964; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ek, Daniel, founder of digital music service, Spotify, is driven by a desire to solve interesting problems. In this fascinating lecture, moderated by KPCB's Chi-Hua Chien, Ek shares his thoughts on leadership, collaboration, and a laser-focus on building truly great products.
  - Ek, Daniel, Entrepreneurship as Problem-Solving, 2012-05-16; 2965; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel shares his very early experiences with entrepreneurship, which came about due to a need to solve problems. Ek also provides his definition of an entrepreneur, as "someone that has an itch for a problem, and is annoyed enough by that problem to seek a solution for it."
  - Ek, Daniel, Execution is 95 Percent, 2012-05-16; 2966; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ek, Daniel describes advantages and challenges in co-founding Spotify and in being a young entrepreneur. A focus on seeing the solution, mixed with a natural tenacity to execute on ideas, will see the right people through, says Ek, as "ideas are five percent, and execution is 95 percent."
  - Ek, Daniel, The Big, Hairy, Audacious Goal of Spotify, 2012-05-16; 2967; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel explains the big goal behind Spotify, in response to a question from KPCB venture capitalist Chi-Hua Chien. Ek articulates Spotify's goal to create a social music service that was more attractive than piracy for consumers that also allowed the music industry to grow.
  - Ek, Daniel, Solving a World of Product Problems, 2012-05-16; 2968; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel explains his approach to building products to solve problems, with KPCB venture capitalist Chi-Hua Chien. Ek credits his engineering background and the ability to test product iterations as key components in his approach. He also discusses the importance of streamlined user interfaces, the opportunity to leverage global platforms to reach audiences at scale, and being selective in addressing the right customer use cases.
  - Ek, Daniel, Leading Distributed Teams, 2012-05-16; 2969; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel shares how he manages to lead a growing company with a workforce distributed on multiple continents. "I don't think the physical experience can be replaced yet," says Ek, who admits to traveling extensively and sitting out in the open to encourage conversations in his company's offices. In conversation with KPCB venture capitalist Chi-Hua Chien, Ek also describes the virtual town hall meetings he conducts to maintain transparent communication.
  - Ek, Daniel, Don't Say Yes to Everything, 2012-05-16; 2970; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel examines some of the mistakes he has made as a serial entrepreneur. Chief among them, says Ek, is saying 'yes' to everything and trying to do too much at once, which never works out. Ek also articulates the dangers of waiting too long in hiring and firing team members within a quickly growing organization. Especially in a small company, "everyone needs to carry their weight, and more," says Ek.
  - Ek, Daniel, Opportunities in Sensors and Smart Devices, 2012-05-16; 2971; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    In conversation with KPCB venture capitalist Chi-Hua Chien, Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel offers his vision of the future, and shares some of technologies he sees as ripe for entrepreneurial opportunities in the coming years. Ek is particularly interested in the growing data that will be available as sensors become more common in smart products and devices.
  - Ek, Daniel, Product Innovations Can Reduce Piracy, 2012-05-16; 2972; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    A few people will always pirate content, says Spotify Co-Founder Ek, Daniel, but the vast majority just want convenient access to digital content. Ek credits Spotify as bringing to market a legal and enjoyable alternative to pirating content, and he identifies other media industries that need to address this challenge.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Secrets at Apple's Core [Entire Talk], 2012-05-23; 2973; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Lashinsky, Adam, Fortune senior editor-at-large, shares an insider look at Apple, one of the world's most iconic and secretive companies. Based on his research into the technology giant's internal processes and approaches to leadership and building products, Lashinsky offers insights and surprises from his book, Inside Apple: How America's Most Admired--and Secretive--Company Really Works.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Do You Need to be Steve Jobs?, 2012-05-23; 2974; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Do you need to be and act like Steve Jobs to mirror the success the late co-founder created as the head of Apple? While the answer is no, says Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam, entrepreneurs should carefully examine how Jobs ran Apple and choose from the many applicable lessons that fly in the face of traditional business practice.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, When Steve Jobs Returned to Apple, 2012-05-23; 2975; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam explains the challenges faced by Apple when co-founder Steve Jobs returned to the company in 1997. With the company on the verge of insolvency, Lashinsky discusses what actions Jobs took to streamline the product line, fix supply chain operations, and unify the company's branding.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Keeping Company Secrets, 2012-05-23; 2976; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Based on his research into the inner workings of Apple, Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam describes the premium the company places on keeping secrets, even when it comes to internal communications and processes. According to Lashinsky, Apple's commitment to secrecy often includes employees only seeing finished products they worked on once the products are revealed to the general public.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Every Detail Matters, 2012-05-23; 2977; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam shares examples of how Apple, and late co-founder Steve Jobs, obsessed over the smallest product details.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Insanely Great Integration, 2012-05-23; 2978; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Part of Apple's success is due to the company's ability to integrate hardware and software, says Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam. Here the author of Inside Apple explains how the company wins by using a classic vertical integration model, saying 'no' to unnecessary features, and also excels at innovation by allowing product design to lead over engineering or financial concerns.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Directly Responsible Individuals, 2012-05-23; 2979; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam describes how Apple maintains accountability in project development through the identification of a DRI: Directly Responsible Individual. Lashinsky also discusses other aspects of Apple's unique culture, including the lack of general managers and allowing teams to work in a start-up manner within the larger organization.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Stay on Simple Messages, 2012-05-23; 2980; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Creating clear and compelling messaging is key to Apple's marketing approach, says Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam. Moreover, the company compounds success in this area by staying on a unified message. Lashinsky also shares an amusing example of how Apple reminds its employees to strive for simplicity.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Leadership Questions for Apple, 2012-05-23; 2981; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Fortune magazine Senior Editor Lashinsky, Adam describes the leadership challenge Apple now faces following the death of co-founder Steve Jobs. This is a major question facing the company, says Lashinsky, as "Today, Apple is not led by entrepreneurs." Lashinsky also outlines the backgrounds and experience of Apple's current upper management team.
  - Lashinsky, Adam, Doing the Best Work of Your Career, 2012-05-23; 2982; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Apple is a culture of work; it's not a culture of play, says Inside Apple author Lashinsky, Adam. In response to a question comparing the cultures of Apple and Google, Lashinsky agrees the two are diametrically opposed, and that Apple sees little value in trying to "entertain its employees." While Apple is a demanding environment, says Lashinsky, many employees love the experience as they are given the opportunity to do the best work of their careers.
  - Houston, Drew, Finding Your Way as an Entrepreneur [Entire Talk], 2012-05-30; 2983; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Co-Founder Houston, Drew shares personal moments from starting the cloud-based file storage service Dropbox. Houston touches on the importance of persevering through early challenges at a startup, selecting the right co-founder, and focusing on solving problems to maximize customer happiness.
  - Houston, Drew, It's Not About Checking Off Boxes, 2012-05-30; 2984; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    There's a bunch of different paths to success, says entrepreneur Houston, Drew. Here the co-founder of Dropbox explains why founding companies is not about "checking off boxes" from a list, and encourages entrepreneurs to embrace the fact that they won't have all the answers.
  - Houston, Drew, Motivated to Solve a Problem, 2012-05-30; 2985; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Co-Founder Houston, Drew tells the origin story of Dropbox, his cloud-based online file storage company. Houston admits going after an idea in what was a crowded space, but explains the personal pain points that drove him to create the first version of his product.
  - Houston, Drew, How I Met My Co-Founder, 2012-05-30; 2986; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Dropbox CEO Houston, Drew describes how he met his co-founder, Arash Ferdowsi. After a visit to Silicon Valley, Houston and Ferdowsi were introduced and decided they would work together on the project. While it worked out great, says Houston, "It was kind of like getting married on the first date."
  - Houston, Drew, Learning Happens One Day at a Time, 2012-05-30; 2987; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Dropbox Co-Founder Houston, Drew believes false mythologies about tech company founders do a disservice to aspiring entrepreneurs. While many people think all tech founders start with world conquering visions, says Houston, the reality is that founders learn one day at a time just like everyone else.
  - Houston, Drew, Distribution and Growing Your User Base, 2012-05-30; 2988; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Dropbox Co-Founder Houston, Drew, the need for product distribution strategies is often overlooked at startups. Here he shares some of the mistakes he made around this issue and some of the guerilla-style successes the company achieved to grow their user base.